<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Latest News | Sam Tiéfolo Diabaté</title>
    <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Latest News</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Samuel Tiéfolo Diabaté</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://SamuelDi.github.io/media/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Latest News</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>A look back at last summer OSNAP cruise aboard the RRS James Cook.</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-12-03-jc238/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-12-03-jc238/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spend last Summer at the Scottish Association for Marine Science (SAMS) in Scotland as a visiting PhD scientist working alongside Dr. Neil Fraser, a brilliant researcher with great knowledge of the European slope current and the Atlantic overturning meridional circulation. In July I had the opportunity to join a SAMS delegation of researcher, technicians and students to take part in the 2022 campaign of the Overturning in the Subpolar North Atlantic Program (OSNAP) whose primary aim was to turn around the main observing array of the &amp;lsquo;conveyor belt&amp;rsquo; circulation in the subpolar North Atlantic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlantic_meridional_overturning_circulation&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Atlantic Overturning Meridional Circulation (AMOC)&lt;/a&gt; is a system of northward surface currents and equatorward deep currents in the North Atlantic forming the Great Ocean Conveyor Belt. It plays a major role in the redistribution of heat on our planet, therefore affecting the climate we live in. The AMOC is driven by subtle thermohaline density differences in the ocean, and is projected to collapse in the coming centuries due to anthropogenic emissions of greenhouse gases in the atmosphere. Such collapse would have catastrophic influences on Northern Hemisphere temperature and precipitation regimes, and on on North Atlantic sea levels, among other things. The AMOC is hence particularly observed. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.o-snap.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Overturning in the Subpolar North Atlantic Program (OSNAP)&lt;/a&gt; is an observational mooring array which monitors the strength of the AMOC. It consists of numerous moorings anchored between the Labrador province of Canada, the southern tip of Greenland and Scotland (see schematic below).&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-osnap-array-schematic-mooring-positions-are-indicated-by-the-black-vertical-lines-while-yellow-circular-markers-represent-floatations-and-red-circular-markers-sensors-the-system-of-currents-of-the-amoc-and-of-the-subpolar-gyre-is-also-represented-image-credit-osnaphttpswwwo-snaporg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;
        &lt;img alt=&#34;OSNAP array schematic. Mooring positions are indicated by the black vertical lines, while yellow circular markers represent floatations and red circular markers, sensors. The system of currents of the AMOC and of the subpolar gyre is also represented. Image credit: [OSNAP](https://www.o-snap.org/).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/JC238/osnap_array_schematic_20160401_huaae47369661446ceaaba7720e444a92b_2139765_65c07f138cf4da3c79163c2e0385a2cf.jpg 400w,
               /media/JC238/osnap_array_schematic_20160401_huaae47369661446ceaaba7720e444a92b_2139765_fa31451aea449c68fd272d9d69139777.jpg 760w,
               /media/JC238/osnap_array_schematic_20160401_huaae47369661446ceaaba7720e444a92b_2139765_1200x1200_fit_q100_lanczos.jpg 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/media/JC238/osnap_array_schematic_20160401_huaae47369661446ceaaba7720e444a92b_2139765_65c07f138cf4da3c79163c2e0385a2cf.jpg&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;396&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      OSNAP array schematic. Mooring positions are indicated by the black vertical lines, while yellow circular markers represent floatations and red circular markers, sensors. The system of currents of the AMOC and of the subpolar gyre is also represented. Image credit: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.o-snap.org/&#34;&gt;OSNAP&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main goal of our cruise, labelled JC238, was to turn around moorings deployed between the Icelandic Basin and Scotland during the previous campaign (2020), allowing to maintain and extend OSNAP as an 8 year old ocean observing system. Turning moorings around is essential to retrieve data collected by moored instruments and to allow for their reconditioning and redeployment. For each mooring, a retrieval of the old line and deployment of a new one must be performed. During the former, the mooring line with its instruments are brought in aboard the ship. Deployment is the reverse operation, where a new line with re-fitted instruments is put in the water. Both operations typically last several hours (depending on mooring line length and number of instruments installed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The JC238 campaign took place between July 8th and July 31st, 2022 on the Royal Research Vessel James Cook, which we embarked in Southampton &amp;mdash; right in front of the National Oceanography Centre. The James Cook is a large ship for a research vessel, and certainly is the biggest I sailed on. It can host 30+ scientists on board, and approximately 20 crew and technicians. &lt;!-- A picture of the ship at quay prior to our departure can be found in the Tweet below  --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;It&amp;#39;s proving to be a busy week for our Research Ships!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Today &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/RRSJamesCook?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#RRSJamesCook&lt;/a&gt; departed to the North Atlantic Subpolar Gyre on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/JC238?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#JC238&lt;/a&gt;. Learn more about the work here 💡 &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/iSkhLRQorv&#34;&gt;https://t.co/iSkhLRQorv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Follow &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/uk_osnap?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@uk_osnap&lt;/a&gt; for updates on the expedition!&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/NMF?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#NMF&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/OceanExploration?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#OceanExploration&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/OMEjiLH7Bk&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/OMEjiLH7Bk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; National Oceanography Centre (@NOCnews) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/NOCnews/status/1546856717580996608?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 12, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; --&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-aft-deck-during-mooring-operations-image-credit-sam-t-diabaté&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;
        &lt;img alt=&#34;The aft-deck during mooring operations. Image credit: Sam T. Diabaté.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/JC238/20220716_092623_hu805946db9ebdd36ef734c56fb6e0290f_2759069_5b248a100ffd4d834f68249f07e8fe37.jpg 400w,
               /media/JC238/20220716_092623_hu805946db9ebdd36ef734c56fb6e0290f_2759069_e120a7a4ea1ced807b4ac35e4a964abf.jpg 760w,
               /media/JC238/20220716_092623_hu805946db9ebdd36ef734c56fb6e0290f_2759069_1200x1200_fit_q100_lanczos.jpg 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/media/JC238/20220716_092623_hu805946db9ebdd36ef734c56fb6e0290f_2759069_5b248a100ffd4d834f68249f07e8fe37.jpg&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;343&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The aft-deck during mooring operations. Image credit: Sam T. Diabaté.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took the ship two days to sail through the English Channel and Irish Sea all the way to the shelf-edge west of Scotland. From there we proceeded to turn around the OSNAP moorings from east to west, up to approximately the Mid-Atlantic Ridge (see schematic above). There, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://tos.org/oceanography/assets/images/content/35-seim-title.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;US Research Vessel Neil Armstrong&lt;/a&gt; took over as planned to continue turning around moorings towards Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our job done, we sailed back towards the British-Irish Isles. After having picked up a last mooring North of Scotland, the team of SAMS scientists (including me) was dropped off on July 28th in Ardmucknish Bay in front of SAMS, while the rest of the scientists, the technicians and the crew disembarked in Southampton on July 31st.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-unscrewing-from-its-syntactic-buoy-a-long-range-adcp-after-it-was-brought-in-the-hangar-pic-taken-by-dr-lewis-drysdale&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;
        &lt;img alt=&#34;Unscrewing from its syntactic buoy a long-range ADCP, after it was brought in the hangar. Pic taken by Dr. Lewis Drysdale. &#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/JC238/image014_hu9b10675dd1c3e30223ffd26e9e173130_955813_d95d63a085ef556a8ce1fc5fb01185f8.png 400w,
               /media/JC238/image014_hu9b10675dd1c3e30223ffd26e9e173130_955813_b5443f8aad8aea1ffcfb93c36b590597.png 760w,
               /media/JC238/image014_hu9b10675dd1c3e30223ffd26e9e173130_955813_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/media/JC238/image014_hu9b10675dd1c3e30223ffd26e9e173130_955813_d95d63a085ef556a8ce1fc5fb01185f8.png&#34;
               width=&#34;570&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Unscrewing from its syntactic buoy a long-range ADCP, after it was brought in the hangar. Pic taken by Dr. Lewis Drysdale.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the ship, I worked as part of the SAMS mooring operation team together with Dr. Lewis Drysdale and Estelle Dumont. We worked in close relationship with the UK National Marine Facilities (NMF) technicians onboard. During mooring retrievals and deployments, I assisted Lewis and Estelle on the aft-deck of the ship. Prior to turnarounds, we calibrated and prepared sensors to be deployed. We fitted them with new batteries, set sampling parameters and checked their good operation. For calibration, we mounted the temperature and salinity sensors (microCATS) on the CTD rosette which was casted to perform calibration dips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also in charge of the editing and processing of current-meter data obtained from the moored ADCP (Acoustic Doppler Current Profiler) instruments. Lastly, I was tasked with half a dozen of marine mammal watches. These had to be completed before ramping up the swath sonar bathymetry imaging, which can be harmful to marine mammals. I was specifically trained as a marine mammal observer prior to the campaign and particularly enjoyed doing this job during JC238.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-step-forward-in-time-with-adeola-dahunsi-the-picture-on-the-left-was-taken-in-december-2018-when-adeola-and-i-were-classmates-of-the-master-_oceanography--applications_-this-particular-shot-was-taken-during-fieldwork-on-the-nokoué-lake-benin-four-years-later-jc238-allowed-us-to-meet-again-we-took-the-awesome-selfie-shown-on-the-right-a-couple-of-hours-before-i-disembarked-in-ardmucknish-bay-with-the-other-sams-scientists-image-credit-adeola-dahunsi--sam-diabaté&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;
        &lt;img alt=&#34;**A step forward in time with Adeola Dahunsi**. The picture on the **left** was taken in December 2018, when Adeola and I were classmates of the Master _Oceanography \&amp;amp; Applications_. This particular shot was taken during fieldwork on the Nokoué lake, Benin. **Four years later**, JC238 allowed us to meet again. We took the awesome selfie shown on the **right** a couple of hours before I disembarked in Ardmucknish Bay with the other SAMS scientists. Image credit: Adeola Dahunsi \&amp;amp; Sam Diabaté.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/JC238/PROFDAM2_hu8eddd0a2bb778c47f9741c2b7739c9cb_5832901_b9070325208b778467b83f1e7bc1b44f.png 400w,
               /media/JC238/PROFDAM2_hu8eddd0a2bb778c47f9741c2b7739c9cb_5832901_8dfcde20b493a07a580a0c51103c6529.png 760w,
               /media/JC238/PROFDAM2_hu8eddd0a2bb778c47f9741c2b7739c9cb_5832901_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/media/JC238/PROFDAM2_hu8eddd0a2bb778c47f9741c2b7739c9cb_5832901_b9070325208b778467b83f1e7bc1b44f.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;502&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;A step forward in time with Adeola Dahunsi&lt;/strong&gt;. The picture on the &lt;strong&gt;left&lt;/strong&gt; was taken in December 2018, when Adeola and I were classmates of the Master &lt;em&gt;Oceanography &amp;amp; Applications&lt;/em&gt;. This particular shot was taken during fieldwork on the Nokoué lake, Benin. &lt;strong&gt;Four years later&lt;/strong&gt;, JC238 allowed us to meet again. We took the awesome selfie shown on the &lt;strong&gt;right&lt;/strong&gt; a couple of hours before I disembarked in Ardmucknish Bay with the other SAMS scientists. Image credit: Adeola Dahunsi &amp;amp; Sam Diabaté.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Above all, cruise JC238 was for me an extraordinary human adventure. Lewis and Estelle were exceptionally kind and helpful. I learned a lot alongside them. I am also delighted to have met new colleagues and seen some familiar faces too! In particular I had great pleasure finding Adeola Dahunsi again after several years. Adeola and I were classmates during the academic year 2018 &amp;ndash; 2019. We took the Master &lt;em&gt;Oceanography &amp;amp; Applications&lt;/em&gt; taking place in Cotonou (Benin) and coordinated by University Toulouse III (France) and University of Abomey-Calavi (Benin). At the time, I was coming from Toulouse, while Adeola was joining from Nigeria. At the end of this Master, I went on to start my PhD here in Ireland (in November 2019), while Adeola then studied one year in Ghana before returning to Benin to start a PhD on sea wave dynamics and sediment transport in the Gulf of Guinea. Some of his work can be read &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3390/jmse10111581&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I didn&amp;rsquo;t knew about Adeola would take part in JC238 as a junior scientist, nor did he knew that I was joining with the scientists from SAMS: we only realised we would see each other again a few weeks ahead of the cruise. It was a blessing to see Adeola again. Together we had plenty of fun, and I am very happy that we got to spend a bit of time together. We helped each other out with some of the work too. I was also delighted to meet the other early carreer scientists onboard and wish them all the best in their research career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Today we stopped at Oban to disembark scientists from &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/SAMSoceannews?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@SAMSoceannews&lt;/a&gt; . Next stop &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/NOCnews?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@NOCnews&lt;/a&gt; . Many thanks to everyone for successful expedition and a great team effort. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/JC238?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;JC238&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/xHUw1sq4Lj&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/xHUw1sq4Lj&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; UK OSNAP (@uk_osnap) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/uk_osnap/status/1552693928532606983?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 28, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt; --&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-scientists-and-national-marine-facilities-technicians-aboard-the-rrs-james-cook-during-jc238-the-picture-was-taken-in-ardmucknish-bay-right-before-the-sams-scientists-including-me-disembarked&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;
        &lt;img alt=&#34;Scientists and National Marine Facilities technicians aboard the RRS James Cook during JC238. The picture was taken in Ardmucknish Bay, right before the SAMS scientists (including me!) disembarked.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/JC238/FYxFsnBXgAECRvJ_hu180e9cfb0c41d896bf0b1918f3cf59a3_2231887_70c540a0e7c1e10ac134096971bc9392.jpeg 400w,
               /media/JC238/FYxFsnBXgAECRvJ_hu180e9cfb0c41d896bf0b1918f3cf59a3_2231887_d50a8a275db50856d56ca74501b19be0.jpeg 760w,
               /media/JC238/FYxFsnBXgAECRvJ_hu180e9cfb0c41d896bf0b1918f3cf59a3_2231887_1200x1200_fit_q100_lanczos.jpeg 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/media/JC238/FYxFsnBXgAECRvJ_hu180e9cfb0c41d896bf0b1918f3cf59a3_2231887_70c540a0e7c1e10ac134096971bc9392.jpeg&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Scientists and National Marine Facilities technicians aboard the RRS James Cook during JC238. The picture was taken in Ardmucknish Bay, right before the SAMS scientists (including me!) disembarked.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S.










  
  


&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-Gallery&#34; href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-12-03-jc238/Gallery/20220712_124910.jpg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-12-03-jc238/Gallery/20220712_124910_hu8b5ee91d17f7f1751baaf8eaa8a32982_2370621_0x190_resize_q100_lanczos.jpg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;20220712_124910.jpg&#34; width=&#34;422&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-Gallery&#34; href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-12-03-jc238/Gallery/20220715_145708.jpg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-12-03-jc238/Gallery/20220715_145708_hu0afb60f02c006238c8ad9edfbd0d476b_3143859_0x190_resize_q100_lanczos.jpg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;20220715_145708.jpg&#34; width=&#34;422&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-Gallery&#34; href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-12-03-jc238/Gallery/20220716_092623.jpg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-12-03-jc238/Gallery/20220716_092623_hu805946db9ebdd36ef734c56fb6e0290f_2759069_0x190_resize_q100_lanczos.jpg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;20220716_092623.jpg&#34; width=&#34;422&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-Gallery&#34; href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-12-03-jc238/Gallery/20220716_131207.jpg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-12-03-jc238/Gallery/20220716_131207_hubcc4855ad48e8db4cf1ae81bf21b6448_2707023_0x190_resize_q100_lanczos.jpg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;20220716_131207.jpg&#34; width=&#34;422&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-Gallery&#34; href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-12-03-jc238/Gallery/20220724_084027.jpg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-12-03-jc238/Gallery/20220724_084027_hu77e8f008be8e5acc65fb4514d0a3e513_2152230_0x190_resize_q100_lanczos.jpg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;20220724_084027.jpg&#34; width=&#34;422&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-Gallery&#34; href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-12-03-jc238/Gallery/20220726_080933.jpg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-12-03-jc238/Gallery/20220726_080933_hu55248b167327ea07ced5e3a85bb7b3c2_2748877_0x190_resize_q100_lanczos.jpg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;20220726_080933.jpg&#34; width=&#34;422&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-Gallery&#34; href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-12-03-jc238/Gallery/20220728_153804.jpg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-12-03-jc238/Gallery/20220728_153804_hu0447498dd417af72cd55bd4941c3ca91_2870681_0x190_resize_q100_lanczos.jpg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;20220728_153804.jpg&#34; width=&#34;422&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recovering German and Irish moorings Southwest of Ireland. A campaign on the new Irish Research Vessel (RV) Tom Crean.</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-10-15-tc22008/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-10-15-tc22008/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The one-week long Aimsir/EirOOS survey ended a couple of weeks ago and was the first physical oceanography campaign of the new Irish Research Vessel (RV) Tom Crean. Our primary goal was to recover three moorings located southwest of Ireland, on an offshore underwater plateau known as Goban Spur. This campaign was carried out as a collaboration between three different ocean research institutions: 1) Maynooth University with scientists from the A4 project; 2) the Marine Institute; and 3) the Federal Maritime and Hydrographic Agency of Germany (in German, Bundesamt für Seeschifffahrt und Hydrographie, or BSH).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mooring_%28oceanography%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Moorings&lt;/a&gt; are instrument arrays anchored on the sea floor which sample the water column for an extended amount of time (from months to years). In recent years, a network of moorings has been measuring water properties at the Goban Spur (13&lt;span&gt;°&lt;/span&gt;E, 49&lt;span&gt;°&lt;/span&gt;N). In 2016, German scientists of BSH (the Federal Maritime and Hydrographic Agency of Germany) deployed three &lt;strong&gt;EB&lt;/strong&gt; moorings on the deeper part of the Goban Spur, while in 2020, the Marine Institute filled in the gap between the German moorings and the Irish coastline with additional &lt;strong&gt;EBS&lt;/strong&gt; moorings. The mooring geographical locations, reminding of the &amp;lsquo;OMEX&amp;rsquo; mooring array deployed in the mid-90s, were chosen to close the eastern boundary of the NOAC line, a basinwide mooring array measuring the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlantic_meridional_overturning_circulation&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;North Atlantic conveyor belt circulation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-general-bathymetry-map-of-the-region-southwest-of-ireland-showing-also-the-mooring-locations-as-colour-filled-circle-as-well-as-the-planned-and-effective-ctd-stations-displayed-as-light-and-dark-crosses-the-mobilisation-and-demobilisation-ports-respectfully-cork-and-galway-are-also-indicated-despite-being-indicated-here-ebs5-was-not-recovered-b-zoom-in-on-the-goban-spur-where-most-of-the-action-took-place-markers-are-the-same-as-on-a-only-planned-ctd-stations-are-not-shown--image-credit-gerard-d-mccarthy&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;
        &lt;img alt=&#34;(a) General bathymetry map of the region Southwest of Ireland, showing also the mooring locations as colour filled circle) as well as the planned and effective CTD stations displayed as light and dark crosses. The mobilisation and demobilisation ports, respectfully Cork and Galway, are also indicated. Despite being indicated here, EBS5 was not recovered. (b) Zoom in on the Goban Spur, where most of the action took place. Markers are the same as on (a), only planned CTD stations are not shown.  **Image credit: Gerard D. McCarthy**.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/TC22008/map_hu6d4f72be8b37c9b33c1c1055d4ee3ab5_358051_229adcbf69cf768e9ae1206207195d92.png 400w,
               /media/TC22008/map_hu6d4f72be8b37c9b33c1c1055d4ee3ab5_358051_d069ba76b37e0e9727f9c0ac07d2a970.png 760w,
               /media/TC22008/map_hu6d4f72be8b37c9b33c1c1055d4ee3ab5_358051_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/media/TC22008/map_hu6d4f72be8b37c9b33c1c1055d4ee3ab5_358051_229adcbf69cf768e9ae1206207195d92.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;396&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      (a) General bathymetry map of the region Southwest of Ireland, showing also the mooring locations as colour filled circle) as well as the planned and effective CTD stations displayed as light and dark crosses. The mobilisation and demobilisation ports, respectfully Cork and Galway, are also indicated. Despite being indicated here, EBS5 was not recovered. (b) Zoom in on the Goban Spur, where most of the action took place. Markers are the same as on (a), only planned CTD stations are not shown.  &lt;strong&gt;Image credit: Gerard D. McCarthy&lt;/strong&gt;.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While moorings EB2 and EBS3 were lost, possibly due to trawling activity, three Goban Spur moorings (EB3, EB1 and EBS1) and one shallow mooring (EBS5) sampled the ocean for an extended period. Recovery of these moorings was the primary goal of our cruise. These mooring locations are shown on the map above. The campaign was conducted on the RV Tom Crean between September 24th and 30th, and the principal investigator was Dr. Gerard McCarthy, my PhD supervisor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Maynooth University team, which was composed of Dr. Gerard McCarthy, Dr. Levke Caesar, Dr. André Düsterhus, Dr. Samantha Hallam, Dr. Stephen Ogungbenro and myself, met up with Dr. Manuela Köllner and Tobias Svensson from BSH on the Friday 23/09. We embarked the RV Tom Crean on the following day, joining Dr. Eoghan Daly, Alan Berry and Conall O&#39; Malley from the Marine Institute as well as the ship&amp;rsquo;s crew. We set sail on that day. Mooring EB3 was recovered on Monday 26/09. Rougher weather hindered mooring recovery until the Thursday 29/09, and the elapsed time was used as best as possible to conduct CTD profiles &lt;a href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-05-08-ce22008/&#34;&gt;(Don&amp;rsquo;t know what CTD stations are? Find out more info here)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-dr-gerard-mccarthy-and-dr-eoghan-daly-on-a-coffee-break-image-credit-sam-t-diabaté&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;
        &lt;img alt=&#34;Dr. Gerard McCarthy and Dr. Eoghan Daly on a coffee break. **Image credit: Sam T. Diabaté.**&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/TC22008/20220926_143733_hu69bdb8a02d0705858fa75bf86dc324cf_2819042_35aab319aea530db4078a5bd63249d65.jpg 400w,
               /media/TC22008/20220926_143733_hu69bdb8a02d0705858fa75bf86dc324cf_2819042_5859f8825aef65556a0c98b7b08929dd.jpg 760w,
               /media/TC22008/20220926_143733_hu69bdb8a02d0705858fa75bf86dc324cf_2819042_1200x1200_fit_q100_lanczos.jpg 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/media/TC22008/20220926_143733_hu69bdb8a02d0705858fa75bf86dc324cf_2819042_35aab319aea530db4078a5bd63249d65.jpg&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;343&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Dr. Gerard McCarthy and Dr. Eoghan Daly on a coffee break. &lt;strong&gt;Image credit: Sam T. Diabaté.&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mooring EBS1 and EB1 were recovered on the Thursday 29/09, and it was decided to sail towards land immediately after because of the sea condition worsening. We fled ahead of the storm and reached  &amp;mdash; not without trouble  &amp;mdash;  Galway Bay on the evening of Friday 29/09. We disembarked on the following morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- On this cruise my primary role was to assist with mooring operations, as I had done previously aboard the RRS James Cook.--&gt; Together with Dr. Samantha Hallam, I cleaned up the moored instruments recovered from the mooring lines, downloaded the data from the MicroCATs, set up the instruments for calibration dips, and more broadly facilitated the smooth running of the mooring operations headed by Dr. Manuela Köllner (for EB1 and EB3) and Conall O&#39; Malley (for EBS1).
&lt;p&gt;I was also in charge of the Vessel Mounted Acoustic Doppler Current Profiler (VmADCP), which is an instrument designed to measure the water velocity (currents) of the water column below the ship keel. The VmADCP aboard the RV Tom Crean is a Pinnacle 45 from Teledyne RDI, a particularly modern instrument which allows to perform a novel acquisition method referred to as &amp;lsquo;interleaved&amp;rsquo;. This new method comes with new processing challenges, which I was able to circumvent with help of Pr. Jules Hummon of University of Hawaii who was contacted by mail. Next month, Gerard and I will be taking part in a workshop organised by Dr. Eoghan Daly on VmADCP acquisition and data processing.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-rv-tom-crean-in-galway-harbour-on-demobilisation-day-image-credit-sam-t-diabaté&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;
        &lt;img alt=&#34;The RV Tom Crean in Galway harbour on demobilisation day. **Image credit: Sam T. Diabaté.**&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/TC22008/20221001_102944_hue5f86fdfe6aec3860d9f48206f355920_2750915_301d9ca3f49507df54f319e987f5e19b.jpg 400w,
               /media/TC22008/20221001_102944_hue5f86fdfe6aec3860d9f48206f355920_2750915_2d4db9c38970e6601c697ad737f811c0.jpg 760w,
               /media/TC22008/20221001_102944_hue5f86fdfe6aec3860d9f48206f355920_2750915_1200x1200_fit_q100_lanczos.jpg 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/media/TC22008/20221001_102944_hue5f86fdfe6aec3860d9f48206f355920_2750915_301d9ca3f49507df54f319e987f5e19b.jpg&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;343&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The RV Tom Crean in Galway harbour on demobilisation day. &lt;strong&gt;Image credit: Sam T. Diabaté.&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!-- 













&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-scientists-and-crew-during-tc22008-image-credit-conall-o-maley&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;
        &lt;img alt=&#34;Scientists and crew during TC22008. Image credit: Conall O&amp;#39; Maley.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/TC22008/IMG-20220929-WA0002_hu9e491e39fcc61ccf2eba17d695a69660_186183_11f33a99d2206e801e6110858a27677c.jpg 400w,
               /media/TC22008/IMG-20220929-WA0002_hu9e491e39fcc61ccf2eba17d695a69660_186183_acafd82047c8c6f0c490a064f5c6331d.jpg 760w,
               /media/TC22008/IMG-20220929-WA0002_hu9e491e39fcc61ccf2eba17d695a69660_186183_1200x1200_fit_q100_lanczos.jpg 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/media/TC22008/IMG-20220929-WA0002_hu9e491e39fcc61ccf2eba17d695a69660_186183_11f33a99d2206e801e6110858a27677c.jpg&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;429&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Scientists and crew during TC22008. Image credit: Conall O&#39; Maley.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt; --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RV Tom Crean is a very modern ship, with a range of new assets to help scientists conduct research at sea. I was in particular impressed by the features of the dry laboratory. Scientists can now operate the CTD winch from a designated desk in the dry lab, provided the bridge has granted us control. The different screens in the lab are all connected to a central PC unit, and everything is accessible from a server, allowing researchers to quickly work on different ongoing measurements at a time (VmADC Profiling, but also swath bathymetry measurements, underway systems, CTD monitoring, etc.). The ship design makes life aboard comfortable and easy, with a gym, a TV space, a very comfortable dining room facing the galley, and plenty of room to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As on previous cruises I took part in, pods of common dolphins and pilot whales were common encounters. A camera was installed on the hull and allowed to see dolphins having great fun right beneath us. Colleagues Dr. Samantha Hallam and Alan Berry shared some wonderful footages on their social media, some of which can be seen below. Dr. Eoghan Daly also put together a video of our campaign which was shown during the RV Tom Crean commissioning ceremony, and it can be found below too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sam&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LcMYa1LylzU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Dolphins?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#Dolphins&lt;/a&gt; 🐬 yesterday evening guiding the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/MarineInst?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@MarineInst&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Eir_OOS?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Eir_OOS&lt;/a&gt; survey home ahead of the storm. 🥰 &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/EBdpf5HzNf&#34;&gt;https://t.co/EBdpf5HzNf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/YKPG9c4ZAx&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/YKPG9c4ZAx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Alan Berry (@alanpberry) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/alanpberry/status/1575787967863750657?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 30, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Last day at sea and force 8 this morning as we are homeward bound for Galway on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/RVMarineInst?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@RVMarineInst&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/TomCrean?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#TomCrean&lt;/a&gt; we have had plenty of weather, and a lovely video today of the dolphin by the keel &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Eir_OOS?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Eir_OOS&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/a_ceathair?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@a_ceathair&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ICARUS_Maynooth?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@ICARUS_Maynooth&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Maynoothgeog?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Maynoothgeog&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/MarineInst?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@MarineInst&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/tRp5ksAwVV&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/tRp5ksAwVV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Samantha Hallam (@samhallam5) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/samhallam5/status/1575972208752889856?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 30, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Observing the Northeast Atlantic aboard the RV Celtic Explorer!</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-05-08-ce22008/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-05-08-ce22008/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From April 24th to May 6th, I took part in the Marine Institute Ocean Climate Cruise 2022 aboard the Research Vessel Celtic Explorer. This 2-week research cruise led by Chief Scientist Dr. Caroline Cusack aimed to measure water properties in the Northeast Atlantic. To do so we sampled 40+ water depth profiles from Ireland to the southern Rockall Plateau. The campaign was very successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--













&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-view-of-galway-bay-from-the-marine-institute-image-credit-sam-t-diabaté&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;
        &lt;img alt=&#34;View of Galway Bay from the Marine Institute. Image credit: Sam T. Diabaté.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/CE22008/MI_Backyard_huc6a1712cc0d023d52519b3f2442f36c1_847547_f14d56122090d1066fbfd3d54d5cf8e7.jpeg 400w,
               /media/CE22008/MI_Backyard_huc6a1712cc0d023d52519b3f2442f36c1_847547_8d6b665114951145b13a87079fcbc624.jpeg 760w,
               /media/CE22008/MI_Backyard_huc6a1712cc0d023d52519b3f2442f36c1_847547_1200x1200_fit_q100_lanczos.jpeg 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/media/CE22008/MI_Backyard_huc6a1712cc0d023d52519b3f2442f36c1_847547_f14d56122090d1066fbfd3d54d5cf8e7.jpeg&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;343&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      View of Galway Bay from the Marine Institute. Image credit: Sam T. Diabaté.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since more than a decade, the Marine Institute has been conducting annual Ocean Climate Cruises along a route encompassing the Irish shelf and slope, the Porcupine Bank, the Rockall Trough and ending on the southern Rockall Plateau. This effort allows to monitor temporal changes in water properties such as temperature, salinity, oxygen levels, and flow speed. While satellite observations now play a crucial role in informing scientists about the ocean properties and flow at surface, in-situ measurements obtained thanks to oceanographic cruises remain vital to understand our planet climate, as they inform about the ocean interior. 
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4XfEme2M1IQ&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday 23rd April and Sunday 24th April, scientists boarded RV Celtic Explorer in the Port of Galway and joined the crew already aboard. Later on the Sunday, we set sail and began what was my first ever research campaign at sea. Over the course of the following two weeks, we completed more than forty profiles following the historical route (MIOC# stations, see map below) and two additional transects: the North&amp;ndash;South Porcupine Section and the Erris Head section (again, see map). 













&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-map-of-the-region-with-indication-of-ctd-stations-image-credit-caroline-cusack&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;
        &lt;img alt=&#34;Map of the region with indication of CTD stations. Image credit: Caroline Cusack.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/CE22008/Stations_hu965e895b94a74c089419c4299462429f_4870534_5a2a650d2ea465aaae84a66a10f827f5.jpeg 400w,
               /media/CE22008/Stations_hu965e895b94a74c089419c4299462429f_4870534_81b87050d3c86fdbafceab316bc264e6.jpeg 760w,
               /media/CE22008/Stations_hu965e895b94a74c089419c4299462429f_4870534_1200x1200_fit_q100_lanczos.jpeg 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/media/CE22008/Stations_hu965e895b94a74c089419c4299462429f_4870534_5a2a650d2ea465aaae84a66a10f827f5.jpeg&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;495&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Map of the region with indication of CTD stations. Image credit: Caroline Cusack.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Niskin bottles are used to collect water at different depths. They are mounted on a cylindrical metallic frame (a rosette) which is lowered from the side of the ship down to the ocean floor with use of a large winch. The Niskin bottles allow scientists to measure dissolved oxygen levels as well as other chemical compounds and elements, abundance in phyto/zoo-plankton, metal contents, etc. The rosette is also fitted with a pumped Conductivity/Temperature/Depth (CTD) sensor (a MicroCAT). For this reason, we loosely call the process of lowering the rosette and sampling the water a CTD profile. 













&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-rosette-sitting-on-deck-before-being-lowered-in-the-water-viewed-from-above-it-is-fitted-with-the-niskin-bottles-and-a-pumped-conductivitytemperaturedepth-ctd-measuring-instrument-image-credit-sam-t-diabaté&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;
        &lt;img alt=&#34;The rosette sitting on deck before being lowered in the water (viewed from above). It is fitted with the Niskin bottles and a pumped Conductivity/Temperature/Depth (CTD) measuring instrument. Image credit: Sam T. Diabaté.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/CE22008/Rosette_hu2e11f70184a175835c2e6b9a47085bfe_312900_182fc5b87cbcc102810b0100fc6e7503.jpeg 400w,
               /media/CE22008/Rosette_hu2e11f70184a175835c2e6b9a47085bfe_312900_ab957ba4d42d05093f812762acd14a50.jpeg 760w,
               /media/CE22008/Rosette_hu2e11f70184a175835c2e6b9a47085bfe_312900_1200x1200_fit_q100_lanczos.jpeg 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/media/CE22008/Rosette_hu2e11f70184a175835c2e6b9a47085bfe_312900_182fc5b87cbcc102810b0100fc6e7503.jpeg&#34;
               width=&#34;343&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The rosette sitting on deck before being lowered in the water (viewed from above). It is fitted with the Niskin bottles and a pumped Conductivity/Temperature/Depth (CTD) measuring instrument. Image credit: Sam T. Diabaté.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aboard the RV Celtic Explorer, I was the CTD operator of the night shift team, meaning I was in charge of the PC from which data acquisition and Niskin bottle closure was controlled. I was in permanent radio contact with the winch driver and with the crew members working on deck, so that we could synchronise our actions. I was also in close contact with the bio-geo-chemist team lead (Dr. Janina V. Büscher), who would correspond to me depth levels of interest prior to each CTD profile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;M6 buoy successfully deployed from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/RVCelticExplorer?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#RVCelticExplorer&lt;/a&gt; this week during CE22008 annual climate monitoring survey 2022. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/MarineInst?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@MarineInst&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Eir_OOS?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Eir_OOS&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/Z31jP0bxHy&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/Z31jP0bxHy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Marine Institute Research Vessels (@RVMarineInst) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/RVMarineInst/status/1519930447379275776?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;April 29, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the CTD profiles, we also turned around the M6 subsurface mooring and the M6 weather buoy. Moorings (and buoys) are measurement arrays which permanently stay at sea and therefore need regular refitting. The above tweet feature a nice drone video shot when we dropped the M6 buoy anchor in the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, we frequently enjoyed the company of marine mammals. We saw a large pod of common dolphins, and several pods of pilot whales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further pictures of the ship can be found below. Image credit: Sam T. Diabaté. From top to bottom:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Galway Port, with the RV Celtic Explorer in the entrance of the harbour prior to mobilisation,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ship aft-deck seen from outside the bridge deck,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ship aft-deck seen from outside the dry lab on the forecastle deck,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ship forecastle deck, from outside the bridge on the wheelhouse deck.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sam










  
  


&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-Gallery&#34; href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-05-08-ce22008/Gallery/a.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-05-08-ce22008/Gallery/a_hu4b9cf7451da1507ba3a7ec08367e67d3_742112_0x190_resize_q100_lanczos.jpeg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;a.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;422&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-Gallery&#34; href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-05-08-ce22008/Gallery/b.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-05-08-ce22008/Gallery/b_huafe8f738a69ea0b4eaf10c75528e7878_780631_0x190_resize_q100_lanczos.jpeg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;b.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;422&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-Gallery&#34; href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-05-08-ce22008/Gallery/c.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-05-08-ce22008/Gallery/c_huaa0dbf39228d256d12ac7924001c605d_827466_0x190_resize_q100_lanczos.jpeg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;c.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;422&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-Gallery&#34; href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-05-08-ce22008/Gallery/d.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/22-05-08-ce22008/Gallery/d_hu71b2ee42e6826570c4c0613922ccd352_608806_0x190_resize_q100_lanczos.jpeg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;d.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;422&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The A4 annual meeting took place today!</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/21-11-18-a4-annual-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/21-11-18-a4-annual-meeting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today (Nov 18, 2021), the A4 team hosted the A4 annual meeting and presented some of their latest research material. In the past year, our team has grown bigger and is now more than ever a very exciting environment to work in. Not everyone is there on this picture, but there is (from left to right): Levke Caesar (WP1), Niamh Cahill (WP2), Samantha Hallam (ROADMAP), Maeve Upton (WP2), André Düsterhus (WP2), Emma Worthington (NOC) (top row), Gerard McCarthy (WP1), Catherine O&amp;rsquo;Beirne (WP2), me (WP1), Zoe Roseby (WP3), Fermin Alvarez (WP3) (bottom row).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A4 (Aigéin, Aeráid, agus athrú Atlantaigh) is a project led by Gerard McCarthy which looks at Atlantic change, sea level, and decadal climate prediction. It is a project which gathers scientists from different research institute:  the Irish Climate Analysis and Research UnitS (ICARUS, Geography Dpt, Maynooth University), the Hamilton Institute (Maynooth University), and Trinity College Dublin (TCD). Most of us are part of ICARUS, and we effectively make up the oceanography section of this institute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Looking forward to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/a_ceathair?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@a_ceathair&lt;/a&gt; annual meeting today. We&amp;#39;ve had to move everything online so send a message if you&amp;#39;d like to join and I&amp;#39;ll forward the link. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/yZC4jk5OG4&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/yZC4jk5OG4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; A4: Aigéin, Aeráid, &amp;amp; athrú Atlantaigh (@a_ceathair) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/a_ceathair/status/1461226751548264450?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;November 18, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first work package (WP1), which I am part of, focuses on the large scale Atlantic variability (currents, heat transport, heat exchanges, etc.). This work package is led by Gerard McCarthy, while Levke Caesar and I complete the team.  We work in strong connection with ROADMAP member Samantha Hallam, and PhD workers Emma Worthington (National Oceanography Centre Southampton) and Jamie Matthews (Imperial College London). We study the variability of the Gulf Stream, of the Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation (AMOC), and more broadly of the currents that make up the North Atlantic. Gerard and I also study the sea-level variability, and we are particularly interested in coastal areas, where sea-level changes are of upmost importance to humankind. Levke and Gerard have a long-standing interest for the AMOC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second package (WP2) is led by André Düsterhus and focuses on seasonal to decadal prediction (forecast, but on long timescales). Their work is made using statistical methods of prediction, and the outcomes of their research is quite diverse. For example, they try to create better prediction of the North Atlantic Oscillation and/or of others important proxies for Ireland weather using sea surface information (temperatures, in particular). They also work on forecasting fish population displacement around Ireland. A part of the team is also strongly focusing on statistical models of geological tide gauges, in link with work package 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The work package 3 (WP3), led by Robin Edwards, is mainly based in Trinity College Dublin and strongly function in connection with the two other work packages. Their efforts focus on reconstructing paleo sea-level variations using geological tide gauges. This is a technique which uses core sampling of salt marsh mud. Water levels are estimated based on the absence/presence of high-marsh/low-marsh species in the sample.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This meeting was an opportunity for me to spend a week in Ireland (I returned to France earlier this year due to the COVID19 outbreak which has forced us to solely work remotely). I was hence able to meet some new colleagues which I had only seen during video meetings. I had two very productive days with Samantha Hallam, working on tide gauge data. I was also able to spend some time with André Düsterhus and Levke Caesar, two colleagues that share my office in Eolas Building, North Campus, Maynooth University. Sadly, the Irish government has now announced that University should return to a strict working from home policy, in the hope to maintain COVID case numbers low. This occurs only two months after allowance to return to the office was announced. This does mean that my stay in France will continue, for now.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One week training in ocean gliders and remotely controlled vehicles in the Canary Islands.</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/21-11-01-plocan-glider-school-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/21-11-01-plocan-glider-school-2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week I followed a one-week training at the Oceanic Platform of the Canary Islands (PLOCAN) focused on ocean glider understanding and manipulation. All information on this glider school can be found here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://gliderschool.eu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://gliderschool.eu/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Underwater gliders are now commonly used to measure ocean properties, from temperature and salinity to current velocities and oxygen levels. They are remotely controlled vehicles which glide through the water. Changing their density by inflating and deflating an external bladder allows to move them forward, while their wings control their direction. They offer a particularly energy efficient alternative to expensive research cruise. Contrarily to traditionally propelled underwater vehicles, they can last months in water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Underwater gliders typically follow a sawtooth pattern when deployed, and they sample the water both during ascent and descent. When surfacing, they exchange information with mission control through Iridium, which is an open ocean internet connection working thanks to satellites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gliders are a part of the fleet at disposition at the Marine Institute, Co. Galway. For our research on the European Slope Currents, a glider was deployed in Spring 2020 on the northwest European shelf-edge. Further deployments are now under examination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Monday 25 October to Friday 29 October, I followed a one-week glider training hosted in PLOCAN, the Oceanographic platform of the Canary Islands. This glider school provided theoretical and practical training in underwater gliders to students coming from Europe and elsewhere in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/OceanGlider?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#OceanGlider&lt;/a&gt; lab still busy &amp;amp; crowded practicing on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/SeaExplorerUUV?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@SeaExplorerUUV&lt;/a&gt; technology setting up glider units for tomorrow’s deployment &amp;amp; piloting in open waters &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/EUMarineRobots?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@EUMarineRobots&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/EuroGOOS?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@EuroGOOS&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Euro_Sea?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Euro_Sea&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Groom2RI?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Groom2RI&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/OceanPractices?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@OceanPractices&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/TechOceanS?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@TechOceanS&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/ICTSNews?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#ICTSNews&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/agenciaiisi?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@agenciaiisi&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/plocan?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@plocan&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/GliderSchool2021?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#GliderSchool2021&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/SkLjWGN9wJ&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/SkLjWGN9wJ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Carlos Barrera (@GliderPLOCAN) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/GliderPLOCAN/status/1453723694820298763?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;October 28, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The glider school allowed me and the other students to manipulate the Slocum and Seaexplorer gliders, respectively from &lt;em&gt;Teledyne&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Alseamar&lt;/em&gt;. We also trained to use a surface vehicle, the Wave Glider from &lt;em&gt;Liquid Robotics&lt;/em&gt;. This vehicle relies on wave energy to move forward, making it, similarly to underwater glider, a (relatively) cheap technology. We had the opportunity to dismantle the gliders, review the remote control options offered by the glider manufacturers, and deploy the vehicles in the ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This glider school was superb in many aspects. I feel very honoured to have met other scientists and doctorands working in subjects related to what I am doing. While the school was hard work, relaxing by the sea in the evening with the others allowed us to get to know one another. The water was as warm as the air (23° C) for most of the week, although the air temperature rose by Friday. This meant we could all enjoy some evening swims, which is an unusual thing to do during the last week of October. Discovering Gran Canaria was indeed a lovely experience.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Our paper on the influence of the Kuroshio and of the Gulf Stream on the nearby coastal sea level is out.</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/21-10-23-firstpublication/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/21-10-23-firstpublication/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Exciting news! 🥳 Our publication on the influence of the Kuroshio and of the Gulf Stream on the nearby coastal sea level is out. This is the first paper that I lead-authored. This paper was published yesterday on the &lt;em&gt;Ocean Science&lt;/em&gt; journal website. The work which led to this paper was entirely supervised by Gerard McCarthy, who is the second main author of this paper. The other co-authors are Didier Swingedouw, Joël Hirschi, Aurélie Duchez, Philip Leadbitter and Ivan Haigh. In this blog post I propose a brief, plain language, summary of our results and their implications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    The entry on my website for this peer-reviewed publication can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/publication/journal-article/os-17-1449-2021/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The article on the publisher website is &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/os-17-1449-2021&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The PDF is freely available &lt;a href=&#34;https://os.copernicus.org/articles/17/1449/2021/os-17-1449-2021.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me give a bit of context first. Due to global warming, sea level is rising across the globe. Interestingly however, this slow process is far from the only driver of sea-level variability. A common example known to most are the tides. Tides make the sea level rise and drop at diurnal and semi-diurnal frequencies (and others, I am not entering details here). Another example is the seasonal cycle: because the water is warmer in summer, water levels are found higher during this period of the year. At longer timescales &amp;mdash; yet shorter than the human-induced sea-level rise &amp;mdash; sea-level changes are dominated by the ocean internal variability. Water within the ocean is slowly moved around through changes in the transport and/or path of oceanic currents, through the westward propagation of eddies (large-scale swirls) or large-scale waves (known as Rossby waves), and through other processes. These mechanisms, together with change in ocean heat content, influence the pluri-annual to multidecadal variability of sea level, in a manner which differs from one location to another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The variability of the sea level along the coast of Japan and of the east USA has received a lot of attention in recent years. This is in part because it is thought to be under the influence of the close-by Kuroshio and Gulf Stream, which are western boundary currents closing the subtropical gyres of the North Pacific and North Atlantic respectively. They are northeastward flowing jets which carry warm water towards high latitudes. A greater appreciation of the sea-level drivers could allow scientists to better understand these western boundary currents which are of great importance to the climate system. Also, the US and Japanese eastern seaboards are two of the most densely populated coastlines in the world. Hence, a greater understanding of sea-level variability in these regions could improve our response to the sea level related threat in a warming world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found that the sea-level variability south of Japan and in the South Atlantic Bight is correlated to the north to south path shifts of the Kuroshio and of the Gulf Stream respectively. To be more precise, the coastal sea level in the upstream region (where the western boundary current flows along the coast) goes up when the western boundary current shifts north downstream of their detachment point. This relationship is illustrated in the figure above, which is adapted from &lt;a href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/talks/egu21/&#34;&gt;one of my talks&lt;/a&gt;. The panels present in shadings the comparison between the coastal sea-level in the US South Atlantic Bight (left) or south of Japan (right) and sea surface velocity magnitudes (well, sort of&amp;hellip; I am keeping it simple here). The shadings represent the difference between sea surface velocity magnitudes averaged over periods of high coastal sea level and over periods of low coastal sea levels. These composites inform us on how the western boundary current paths changed when sea level changed. It is apparent in these panels that sea surface velocity magnitudes drifted to the north when the sea level was high. In both oceans, this relationship had been previously observed, but only for the recent period when satellite measurements are available (that is, in this case, from 1993 onwards). We showed using indices based on ocean temperature profiles and tide gauges that this connection holds for the longer periods of 1948–2019 for the Atlantic and 1968–2019 for the Pacific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exact mechanisms which connects the upstream sea level and the path changes downstream are still unclear and may be relatively involved. Yoshi Sasaki and colleagues proposed that the two were linked through the propagation and breaking of oceanic large-scale waves (thousand of kilometers large!). Their theory, developped for the North Pacific, is particularly interesting. Other theories involve the western boundary current temperature, transport, or upstream paths (as opposed to downstream paths).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thank the anonymous referee as well as Dr. Tal Ezer for their reviewing work. I also thank all my co-authors for their hard work!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    The entry on my website for this peer-reviewed publication can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/publication/journal-article/os-17-1449-2021/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The article on the publisher website is &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/os-17-1449-2021&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The PDF is freely available &lt;a href=&#34;https://os.copernicus.org/articles/17/1449/2021/os-17-1449-2021.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning around the tide gauge in Courtown port, Ireland.</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/21-04-14-turning-around-the-gauge-in-courtown/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/21-04-14-turning-around-the-gauge-in-courtown/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In April 2021, we spend a day with Gerard McCarthy turning around the tide gauge in Courtown harbour, Ireland. Courtown is located south of Dublin and faces the Irish Sea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tides of Courtown are particularly interesting (they are quarter-diurnal at neaps). Changing tides are one of the plausible reasons for the disapearing beach just a few tens of meters to the north of Courtown port. For an in-depth analysis of the effect that this beach disappearance has on place attachment and on individual and community well-being, see the wonderful paper from Chris Phillips (Maynooth University scholar) on solastalgia: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10113-021-01778-y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10113-021-01778-y&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Souvenir from Cotonou, Benin.</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/21-04-05-a-souvenir-from-cotonou/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/21-04-05-a-souvenir-from-cotonou/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A souvenir from Cotonou, Benin, with the other students from the Master 2 &amp;lsquo;Océanographie et applications&amp;rsquo;. This picture was taken in December 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I keep very good memories of my year in Benin, where I pursued my formation in physical oceanography between 2018 and 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This picture was taken in December 2018, in front of the building of the International Chair in Mathematical Physics and Applications (ICMPA), where the courses took place. From left to right: Fernand Assene, Guy-Edgar Milend Mbeh, Thierry Derol Awoulmbang Sakpak, Catherine Jeandel (lecturer, CNRS, Toulouse), Wilfried Domingo, Adeola Dahunsi, Arnaud Kouekam, Léonard Worou, and me. We graduated in September 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us now work in oceanography, meteorology, or related fields. In particular,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fernand works on turbulent mixing and internal tides in the equatorial Atlantic. His first lead-authored paper can be accessed here &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3390/fluids5030147&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.3390/fluids5030147&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arnaud works on dynamical changes of sandy beach in the Gulf of Guinea. Last research can be seen here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1190/INT-2021-0023.1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1190/INT-2021-0023.1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thierry and Adeola have co-authored papers which can be found online.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep an eye out for the others!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Souvenir from Castletownsend, Ireland.</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/21-04-01-a-souvenir-from-castletownsend/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/post/21-04-01-a-souvenir-from-castletownsend/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A souvenir of a field work during the summer 2019 with Gerard McCarthy and David Pugh. This is an ideal way for me to test how to create posts for this website!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We spend a week on the road of Ireland to locate benchmarks from the 19th century and mid-20th century, used for tide gauge leveling at the time. This particular pic of me was taken by David in Castletownsend.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
