<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sam Tiéfolo Diabaté</title>
    <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Sam Tiéfolo Diabaté</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>fr-FR</language><copyright>© Samuel Tiéfolo Diabaté</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://SamuelDi.github.io/media/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Sam Tiéfolo Diabaté</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>(2021) Spreadsheets for GSNW, KEI and tide gauge derived sea-level modes</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/data/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/data/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The following link provides link towards the Gulf Stream North Wall (GSNW) index and the Kuroshio Extension (KE) index presented in the paper &amp;lsquo;Western boundary circulation and coastal sea-level variability in Northern Hemisphere oceans&amp;rsquo; (Diabaté et al; 2021).
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4659318&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4659318&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The publication is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diabaté, S. T., Swingedouw, D., Hirschi, J. J.-M., Duchez, A., Leadbitter, P. J., Haigh, I. D., and McCarthy, G. D.: Western boundary circulation and coastal sea-level variability in Northern Hemisphere oceans, Ocean Sci., 17, 1449–1471, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/os-17-1449-2021&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5194/os-17-1449-2021&lt;/a&gt;, 2021.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To cite these data, please cite the aforementioned paper and the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diabaté, S. T., Swingedouw, D., Hirschi, J. J.-M., Duchez, A., Lead- bitter, P. J., Haigh, I. D., and McCarthy, G. D.: Spreadsheets for GSNW, KEI and tide gauge derived sea-level modes, Zenodo [data set], &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4659318&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4659318&lt;/a&gt;, 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meet the Team</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/people/people/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/people/people/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>(2022) Les variations côtières du niveau de la mer peuvent-elles être influencées par les courants de bord ouest? Illustration avec le Gulf Stream et le Kuroshio.</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/talks/osm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/talks/osm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Le 28 février 2022, j&amp;rsquo;ai donné lors du colloque &lt;strong&gt;Ocean Sciences Meeting 2022&lt;/strong&gt; une présentation intitulée &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Les variations côtières du niveau de la mer peuvent-elles être influencées par les courants de bord ouest? Illustration avec le Gulf Stream et le Kuroshio&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; ou, dans son titre original &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Coastal Sea Level forced by Western Boundary Currents&#39; paths? The example of the Gulf Stream and of the Kuroshio&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Le Gulf Stream, aussi appelé Courant du Golfe en français, et le Kuroshio, qui signifie en japonais le Courant Noir, sont les deux grands courants de bord ouest de l&amp;rsquo;hémisphère nord. Le premier prend source dans le Golfe du Mexique &amp;mdash; qui lui donne son nom &amp;mdash;, contourne la Floride, et longe la côte est des États-Unis d&amp;rsquo;où il se détache à Cap Hatteras pour traverser l&amp;rsquo;Atlantique Nord en direction de l&amp;rsquo;Europe. Le Kuroshio prend quand à lui source à l&amp;rsquo;est de l&amp;rsquo;île philippine de Luçon. Il s&amp;rsquo;écoule entre Taïwan et l&amp;rsquo;archipel japonais des Ryūkyū pour rejoindre le Pacifique au sud du Japon et finalement se détacher du talus continental pour traverser le Pacifique Nord.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Les variations régionales du niveau de la mer engendrées par les changements d&amp;rsquo;intensité et/ou de position de ces deux courants ont été étudiées par de nombreux chercheurs, mais toujours de manière indépendante (c.a.d. sans comparaison entre elles). Avec mes co-auteurs, nous avons mené une étude comparée qui a permis d&amp;rsquo;identifier des points communs dans la manière dont ces courants affectent le niveau de la mer des côtes avoisinantes, mais aussi des divergences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ce sont ces résultats, qui ont par ailleurs fait l&amp;rsquo;objet d&amp;rsquo;une publication scientifique &lt;a href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/publication/journal-article/&#34;&gt;(plus d&amp;rsquo;infos ici)&lt;/a&gt;, que j&amp;rsquo;ai présenté pendant Ocean Sciences Meeting 2022, lors de la session &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Vers une compréhension de la montée du niveau de la mer côtier ainsi que de ses variations&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; ou, &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;OC03, Towards understanding coastal sea-level variability and change&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. Une version de travail de mon intervention durant la conférence peut être lue dans le lecteur ci-dessous. Elle est disponible en anglais seulement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;À cause du COVID19, Ocean Science Meeting 2022 s&amp;rsquo;est tenu de manière totalement virtuelle, comme beaucoup d&amp;rsquo;autres conférences ces deux dernières années. Ceci apporte un important lot de challenges organisationnels. Nonobstant, les sessions qui s&amp;rsquo;intéressaient au niveau de la mer étaient extrêmement intéressantes et ont donné lieu à de remarquable discussions. Je pense que ces discussions ont permis à  chacun d&amp;rsquo;avancer dans sa propre réflexion et ses recherches. Je remercie les organisateurs qui ont fait un excellent travail: Dr. Soenke Dangendorf, Dr. Marta Marcos, Dr. Alejandra Rodriguez Enriquez et Dr. Christopher Piecuch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;








  





&lt;video controls  &gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/media/OSM22_ShortPres.mp4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
Courtesy of OSM22. This is a working version/a draft only. Contrary to what I say towards the end of the video, there was no breakout room after the presentations, but rather a discussion with all presenters and listeners, which was great.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>(2022) Les variations côtières du niveau de la mer peuvent-elles être influencées par les courants de bord ouest? Illustration avec le Gulf Stream et le Kuroshio.</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/talks/osm22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/talks/osm22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Le 28 février 2022, j&amp;rsquo;ai donné lors du colloque &lt;strong&gt;Ocean Sciences Meeting 2022&lt;/strong&gt; une présentation intitulée &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Les variations côtières du niveau de la mer peuvent-elles être influencées par les courants de bord ouest? Illustration avec le Gulf Stream et le Kuroshio&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; ou, dans son titre original &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Coastal Sea Level forced by Western Boundary Currents&#39; paths? The example of the Gulf Stream and of the Kuroshio&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Le Gulf Stream, aussi appelé Courant du Golfe en français, et le Kuroshio, qui signifie en japonais le Courant Noir, sont les deux grands courants de bord ouest de l&amp;rsquo;hémisphère nord. Le premier prend source dans le Golfe du Mexique &amp;mdash; qui lui donne son nom &amp;mdash;, contourne la Floride, et longe la côte est des États-Unis d&amp;rsquo;où il se détache à Cap Hatteras pour traverser l&amp;rsquo;Atlantique Nord en direction de l&amp;rsquo;Europe. Le Kuroshio prend quand à lui source à l&amp;rsquo;est de l&amp;rsquo;île philippine de Luçon. Il s&amp;rsquo;écoule entre Taïwan et l&amp;rsquo;archipel japonais des Ryūkyū pour rejoindre le Pacifique au sud du Japon et finalement se détacher du talus continental pour traverser le Pacifique Nord.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Les variations régionales du niveau de la mer engendrées par les changements d&amp;rsquo;intensité et/ou de position de ces deux courants ont été étudiées par de nombreux chercheurs, mais toujours de manière indépendante (c.a.d. sans comparaison entre elles). Avec mes co-auteurs, nous avons mené une étude comparée qui a permis d&amp;rsquo;identifier des points communs dans la manière dont ces courants affectent le niveau de la mer des côtes avoisinantes, mais aussi des divergences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ce sont ces résultats, qui ont par ailleurs fait l&amp;rsquo;objet d&amp;rsquo;une publication scientifique &lt;a href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/publication/journal-article/&#34;&gt;(plus d&amp;rsquo;infos ici)&lt;/a&gt;, que j&amp;rsquo;ai présenté pendant Ocean Sciences Meeting 2022, lors de la session &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Vers une compréhension de la montée du niveau de la mer côtier ainsi que de ses variations&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; ou, &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;OC03, Towards understanding coastal sea-level variability and change&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. Une version de travail de mon intervention durant la conférence peut être lue dans le lecteur ci-dessous. Elle est disponible en anglais seulement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;À cause du COVID19, Ocean Science Meeting 2022 s&amp;rsquo;est tenu de manière totalement virtuelle, comme beaucoup d&amp;rsquo;autres conférences ces deux dernières années. Ceci apporte un important lot de challenges organisationnels. Nonobstant, les sessions qui s&amp;rsquo;intéressaient au niveau de la mer étaient extrêmement intéressantes et ont donné lieu à de remarquable discussions. Je pense que ces discussions ont permis à  chacun d&amp;rsquo;avancer dans sa propre réflexion et ses recherches. Je remercie les organisateurs qui ont fait un excellent travail: Dr. Soenke Dangendorf, Dr. Marta Marcos, Dr. Alejandra Rodriguez Enriquez et Dr. Christopher Piecuch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;








  





&lt;video controls  &gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/media/OSM22_ShortPres.mp4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
Courtesy of OSM22. This is a working version/a draft only. Contrary to what I say towards the end of the video, there was no breakout room after the presentations, but rather a discussion with all presenters and listeners, which was great.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The A4 annual meeting took place today!</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/post/21-11-18-a4-annual-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/post/21-11-18-a4-annual-meeting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today (Nov 18, 2021), the A4 team hosted the A4 annual meeting and presented some of their latest research material. In the past year, our team has grown bigger and is now more than ever a very exciting environment to work in. Not everyone is there on this picture, but there is (from left to right): Levke Caesar (WP1), Niamh Cahill (WP2), Samantha Hallam (ROADMAP), Maeve Upton (WP2), André Düsterhus (WP2), Emma Worthington (NOC) (top row), Gerard McCarthy (WP1), Catherine O&amp;rsquo;Beirne (WP2), me (WP1), Zoe Roseby (WP3), Fermin Alvarez (WP3) (bottom row).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A4 (Aigéin, Aeráid, agus athrú Atlantaigh) is a project led by Gerard McCarthy which looks at Atlantic change, sea level, and decadal climate prediction. It is a project which gathers scientists from different research institute:  the Irish Climate Analysis and Research UnitS (ICARUS, Geography Dpt, Maynooth University), the Hamilton Institute (Maynooth University), and Trinity College Dublin (TCD). Most of us are part of ICARUS, and we effectively make up the oceanography section of this institute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Looking forward to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/a_ceathair?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@a_ceathair&lt;/a&gt; annual meeting today. We&amp;#39;ve had to move everything online so send a message if you&amp;#39;d like to join and I&amp;#39;ll forward the link. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/yZC4jk5OG4&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/yZC4jk5OG4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; A4: Aigéin, Aeráid, &amp;amp; athrú Atlantaigh (@a_ceathair) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/a_ceathair/status/1461226751548264450?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;November 18, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first work package (WP1), which I am part of, focuses on the large scale Atlantic variability (currents, heat transport, heat exchanges, etc.). This work package is led by Gerard McCarthy, while Levke Caesar and I complete the team.  We work in strong connection with ROADMAP member Samantha Hallam, and PhD workers Emma Worthington (National Oceanography Centre Southampton) and Jamie Matthews (Imperial College London). We study the variability of the Gulf Stream, of the Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation (AMOC), and more broadly of the currents that make up the North Atlantic. Gerard and I also study the sea-level variability, and we are particularly interested in coastal areas, where sea-level changes are of upmost importance to humankind. Levke and Gerard have a long-standing interest for the AMOC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second package (WP2) is led by André Düsterhus and focuses on seasonal to decadal prediction (forecast, but on long timescales). Their work is made using statistical methods of prediction, and the outcomes of their research is quite diverse. For example, they try to create better prediction of the North Atlantic Oscillation and/or of others important proxies for Ireland weather using sea surface information (temperatures, in particular). They also work on forecasting fish population displacement around Ireland. A part of the team is also strongly focusing on statistical models of geological tide gauges, in link with work package 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The work package 3 (WP3), led by Robin Edwards, is mainly based in Trinity College Dublin and strongly function in connection with the two other work packages. Their efforts focus on reconstructing paleo sea-level variations using geological tide gauges. This is a technique which uses core sampling of salt marsh mud. Water levels are estimated based on the absence/presence of high-marsh/low-marsh species in the sample.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This meeting was an opportunity for me to spend a week in Ireland (I returned to France earlier this year due to the COVID19 outbreak which has forced us to solely work remotely). I was hence able to meet some new colleagues which I had only seen during video meetings. I had two very productive days with Samantha Hallam, working on tide gauge data. I was also able to spend some time with André Düsterhus and Levke Caesar, two colleagues that share my office in Eolas Building, North Campus, Maynooth University. Sadly, the Irish government has now announced that University should return to a strict working from home policy, in the hope to maintain COVID case numbers low. This occurs only two months after allowance to return to the office was announced. This does mean that my stay in France will continue, for now.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One week training in ocean gliders and remotely controlled vehicles in the Canary Islands.</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/post/21-11-01-plocan-glider-school-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/post/21-11-01-plocan-glider-school-2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week I followed a one-week training at the Oceanic Platform of the Canary Islands (PLOCAN) focused on ocean glider understanding and manipulation. All information on this glider school can be found here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://gliderschool.eu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://gliderschool.eu/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Underwater gliders are now commonly used to measure ocean properties, from temperature and salinity to current velocities and oxygen levels. They are remotely controlled vehicles which glide through the water. Changing their density by inflating and deflating an external bladder allows to move them forward, while their wings control their direction. They offer a particularly energy efficient alternative to expensive research cruise. Contrarily to traditionally propelled underwater vehicles, they can last months in water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Underwater gliders typically follow a sawtooth pattern when deployed, and they sample the water both during ascent and descent. When surfacing, they exchange information with mission control through Iridium, which is an open ocean internet connection working thanks to satellites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gliders are a part of the fleet at disposition at the Marine Institute, Co. Galway. For our research on the European Slope Currents, a glider was deployed in Spring 2020 on the northwest European shelf-edge. Further deployments are now under examination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Monday 25 October to Friday 29 October, I followed a one-week glider training hosted in PLOCAN, the Oceanographic platform of the Canary Islands. This glider school provided theoretical and practical training in underwater gliders to students coming from Europe and elsewhere in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/OceanGlider?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#OceanGlider&lt;/a&gt; lab still busy &amp;amp; crowded practicing on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/SeaExplorerUUV?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@SeaExplorerUUV&lt;/a&gt; technology setting up glider units for tomorrow’s deployment &amp;amp; piloting in open waters &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/EUMarineRobots?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@EUMarineRobots&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/EuroGOOS?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@EuroGOOS&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Euro_Sea?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Euro_Sea&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Groom2RI?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Groom2RI&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/OceanPractices?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@OceanPractices&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/TechOceanS?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@TechOceanS&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/ICTSNews?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#ICTSNews&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/agenciaiisi?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@agenciaiisi&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/plocan?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@plocan&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/GliderSchool2021?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#GliderSchool2021&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/SkLjWGN9wJ&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/SkLjWGN9wJ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Carlos Barrera (@GliderPLOCAN) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/GliderPLOCAN/status/1453723694820298763?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;October 28, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The glider school allowed me and the other students to manipulate the Slocum and Seaexplorer gliders, respectively from &lt;em&gt;Teledyne&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Alseamar&lt;/em&gt;. We also trained to use a surface vehicle, the Wave Glider from &lt;em&gt;Liquid Robotics&lt;/em&gt;. This vehicle relies on wave energy to move forward, making it, similarly to underwater glider, a (relatively) cheap technology. We had the opportunity to dismantle the gliders, review the remote control options offered by the glider manufacturers, and deploy the vehicles in the ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This glider school was superb in many aspects. I feel very honoured to have met other scientists and doctorands working in subjects related to what I am doing. While the school was hard work, relaxing by the sea in the evening with the others allowed us to get to know one another. The water was as warm as the air (23° C) for most of the week, although the air temperature rose by Friday. This meant we could all enjoy some evening swims, which is an unusual thing to do during the last week of October. Discovering Gran Canaria was indeed a lovely experience.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Our paper on the influence of the Kuroshio and of the Gulf Stream on the nearby coastal sea level is out.</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/post/21-10-23-firstpublication/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/post/21-10-23-firstpublication/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Exciting news! 🥳 Our publication on the influence of the Kuroshio and of the Gulf Stream on the nearby coastal sea level is out. This is the first paper that I lead-authored. This paper was published yesterday on the &lt;em&gt;Ocean Science&lt;/em&gt; journal website. The work which led to this paper was entirely supervised by Gerard McCarthy, who is the second main author of this paper. The other co-authors are Didier Swingedouw, Joël Hirschi, Aurélie Duchez, Philip Leadbitter and Ivan Haigh. In this blog post I propose a brief, plain language, summary of our results and their implications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    The entry on my website for this peer-reviewed publication can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/publication/journal-article/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The article on the publisher website is &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/os-17-1449-2021&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The PDF is freely available &lt;a href=&#34;https://os.copernicus.org/articles/17/1449/2021/os-17-1449-2021.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me give a bit of context first. Due to global warming, sea level is rising across the globe. Interestingly however, this slow process is far from the only driver of sea-level variability. A common example known to most are the tides. Tides make the sea level rise and drop at diurnal and semi-diurnal frequencies (and others, I am not entering details here). Another example is the seasonal cycle: because the water is warmer in summer, water levels are found higher during this period of the year. At longer timescales &amp;mdash; yet shorter than the human-induced sea-level rise &amp;mdash; sea-level changes are dominated by the ocean internal variability. Water within the ocean is slowly moved around through changes in the transport and/or path of oceanic currents, through the westward propagation of eddies (large-scale swirls) or large-scale waves (known as Rossby waves), and through other processes. These mechanisms, together with change in ocean heat content, influence the pluri-annual to multidecadal variability of sea level, in a manner which differs from one location to another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The variability of the sea level along the coast of Japan and of the east USA has received a lot of attention in recent years. This is in part because it is thought to be under the influence of the close-by Kuroshio and Gulf Stream, which are western boundary currents closing the subtropical gyres of the North Pacific and North Atlantic respectively. They are northwestward flowing jet which carry warm water towards high latitudes. A greater appreciation of the sea-level drivers could allow scientists to better understand these western boundary currents which are of great importance to the climate system. Also, the US and Japanese eastern seaboards are two of the most densely populated coastlines in the world. Hence, a greater understanding of sea-level variability in these regions could improve our response to the sea level related threat in a warming world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found that the sea-level variability south of Japan and in the South Atlantic Bight is correlated to the north to south path shifts of the Kuroshio and of the Gulf Stream respectively. To be more precise, the coastal sea level in the upstream region (where the western boundary current flows along the coast) goes up when the western boundary current shifts north downstream of their detachment point. The inverse is also true. This relationship is illustrated in the figure above, which is adapted from &lt;a href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/talks/egu21/&#34;&gt;one of my talks&lt;/a&gt;. The panels present in shadings the comparison between the coastal sea-level in the US South Atlantic Bight (left) or south of Japan (right) and sea surface velocity magnitudes (well, sort of&amp;hellip; I am keeping it simple here). The shadings represent the difference between sea surface velocity magnitudes averaged over periods of high coastal sea level and over periods of low coastal sea levels. This composites informs us on how path of the western boundary current changed when the sea level changed. It is apparent in these panels that sea surface velocity magnitudes drifted to the north when the sea level was high. In both oceans, this relationship had been previously observed, but only for the recent period when satellite measurements are available (that is, in this case, from 1993 onwards). We showed using indices based on ocean temperature profiles and tide gauges that this connection holds for the longer periods of 1948–2019 for the Atlantic and 1968–2019 for the Pacific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exact mechanisms which connects the upstream sea level and the path changes downstream are still unclear an may be relatively involved. Yoshi Sasaki and colleagues proposed that the two were linked through the propagation and breaking of oceanic large-scale waves (thousand of kilometers large!). Their theory, developped for the North Pacific, is particularly interesting. Other theories involve the western boundary current temperature, transport, or upstream paths (as opposed to downstream paths).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thank the anonymous referee as well as Dr. Tal Ezer for their reviewing work. I also thank all my co-authors for their hard work!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    The entry on my website for this peer-reviewed publication can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/publication/journal-article/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The article on the publisher website is &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5194/os-17-1449-2021&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The PDF is freely available &lt;a href=&#34;https://os.copernicus.org/articles/17/1449/2021/os-17-1449-2021.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Western boundary circulation and coastal sea-level variability in Northern Hemisphere oceans</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/publication/journal-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/publication/journal-article/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- &lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    A plain language explanation of the results of the paper and their implications for future research is given in &lt;a href=&#34;https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/post/21-10-23-firstpublication/&#34;&gt;this blog post &lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
 --&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Cliquez sur le bouton &lt;em&gt;DOI&lt;/em&gt; pour avoir accès à l&amp;rsquo;article sur le site internet du journal. Pour télécharger directement la version PDF, cliquez sur &lt;em&gt;PDF&lt;/em&gt;. Pour télécharger les metadatas de citation, cliquez sur le bouton &lt;em&gt;Citation&lt;/em&gt;. Les données décrites dans le papier peuvent être téléchargées en cliquant sur &lt;em&gt;Jeu de données&lt;/em&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- Supplementary notes can be added here, including [code and math](https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/writing-markdown-latex/). --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>(2021) Western boundary circulation and sea level patterns in northern hemisphere oceans</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/talks/egu21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/talks/egu21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I presented some of my work on the link between western boundary current paths and the variability of the nearby coastal sea-level variability at the EGU General Assembly in spring 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning around the tide gauge in Courtown port, Ireland.</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/post/21-04-14-turning-around-the-gauge-in-courtown/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/post/21-04-14-turning-around-the-gauge-in-courtown/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In April 2021, we spend a day with Gerard McCarthy turning around the tide gauge in Courtown harbour, Ireland. Courtown is located south of Dublin and faces the Irish Sea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tides of Courtown are particularly interesting (they are quarter-diurnal at neaps). Changing tides are one of the plausible reasons for the disapearing beach just a few tens of meters to the north of Courtown port. For an in-depth analysis of the effect that this beach disappearance has on place attachment and on individual and community well-being, see the wonderful paper from Chris Phillips (Maynooth University scholar) on solastalgia: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10113-021-01778-y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10113-021-01778-y&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Souvenir from Castletownsend, Ireland</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/post/19-08-01-a-souvenir-from-castletownsend/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/post/19-08-01-a-souvenir-from-castletownsend/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is an ideal test for this first website!
A souvenir of a field work during the summer 2019 with Gerard McCarthy and David Pugh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We spend a week on the road of Ireland to locate benchmarks from the 19th century and mid-20th century, used for tide gauge leveling at the time. This particular pic of me was taken by David in Castletownsend.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Souvenir from Cotonou, Benin</title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/post/18-12-15-a-souvenir-from-cotonou/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/post/18-12-15-a-souvenir-from-cotonou/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A souvenir from Cotonou, Benin, with the other students from the Master 2 &amp;lsquo;Océanographie et applications&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I keep very good memories of my year in Benin, where I pursued my formation in physical oceanography between 2018 and 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This picture was taken in December 2018, in front of the building of the International Chair in Mathematical Physics and Applications (ICMPA), where the courses took place. From left to right: Fernand Assene, Guy-Edgar Milend Mbeh, Thierry Derol Awoulmbang Sakpak, Catherine Jeandel (lecturer, CNRS, Toulouse), Wilfried Domingo, Adeola Dahunsi, Arnaud Kouekam, Léonard Worou, and me. We graduated in September 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us now work in oceanography, meteorology, or related fields. In particular,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fernand works on turbulent mixing and internal tides in the equatorial Atlantic. His first lead-authored paper can be accessed here &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3390/fluids5030147&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.3390/fluids5030147&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arnaud works on dynamical changes of sandy beach in the Gulf of Guinea. Last research can be seen here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1190/INT-2021-0023.1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1190/INT-2021-0023.1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thierry and Adeola have co-authored papers which can be found online.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep an eye out for the others!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/admin/config.yml</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/admin/config.yml</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/contact/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/data/march2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/data/march2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/talks/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://SamuelDi.github.io/fr/talks/example/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
